Willard Thorp and Margaret Farrand Thorp Papers, 1886-1981 (bulk 1930-1970): Finding Aid C0292
Manuscripts Division
- Series 1: Papers of Willard Thorp, 1916-1986; 23 boxes
  - Subseries 1A: Correspondence, 1926-1986; 12 boxes
    - Unidentified Persons, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - University of Washington, 1958-1959; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - V-Ve, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Vincent, Howard, 1945-1963; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Vogel, Bill, 1931; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Vogel, Joe, 1938-1942; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Wainwright, Alexander, 1940-1970; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 12a)
    - W, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Warren, Robert Penn ("Red"), 1944-1981; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Wat-Way, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Weaver, Bill, 1950-1951; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Webster, J. Carson, 1972; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - "The Well of English, Now Defiled, or Why Johnny Can't Write"- Princeton Alumni Weekly, September 26, correspondence, 1958-1966; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Wells-White, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Whiton, A.S. (Pete), 1943-1945; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Whitt-Z, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Subseries 1B: Writings, 1932-1967; 2 boxes
    Includes articles, speeches, contributions to books, and class lecture notes in draft and note form, including "Americana Proving Ground" ( Princeton Alumni Weekly, May 3, 1940), "The Colleges and the Selective Service Act," drafts of "Historical Note" (introductory chapter to Herman Melville's White Jacket), and a checklist of his published writings compiled by Stephen V. Justice (1983). Speeches include "Reading Walden" at the Eleventh Yale Conference on the Teaching of English (April 9-10, 1965), "The Tradition of American Literature at Princeton," a dedication of the Music Building, Princeton University (May 2, 1964), and "English Section II" at the Modern Language Association (1953). Class lecture notes also include lists of students' names and grades. These undergraduate and graduate courses (1932-1967) included Victorian Poets, the Victorian Age, the Age of Dryden, American Literature, Twentieth-Century Literature, the American Novel, and Henry James.
    Arranged by genre of material.
    - 1. Articles, Etc., 1940 May 3-1967 July 21; 1 box
      - "Americana Proving Ground", 1940 May 3; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 1)
        Article and quiz, Princeton Alumni Weekly
      - "The Colleges and the Selective Service Act", dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 2)
      - Melville, Herman, 1967 July 21; 1 box
        - White Jacket, 1967 July 21; 1 box
          - "Historical Note" by Willard Thorp (first draft), dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 3)
          - "Historical Note" by Willard Thorp (second draft), 1967 July 21; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 4)
          - Revisions of section of reviews, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 5)
      - "The Published Writings of Willard Thorp: A Checklist", dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 6)
        compiled by Stephen V. Justice
    - 2. Speeches, 1941 June 8-1965 April 10; 1 box
      - Speeches and articles, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 7)
      - Speech-"Reading Walden"-Eleventh Yale Conference on the Teaching of English, 1965 April 9-10; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 8)
      - Speech-"Right Forms for American Studies?"-Joint Session of the Modern Language Association and American Studies Association, NYC, 1964 December 28; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 9)
      - Speech-"The Tradition of American Literature at Princeton", dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 10)
      - Speech at the Dedication of Music Building-Princeton University, 1964 May 2; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 11)
      - Speeches-"English Section II" -Modern Language Association, 1953; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 12)
      - Tribute to Willard Thorp, M.D. Anderson Visiting Professor-Rice University-by the Owen Wister Literary Society, 1952; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 13)
      - Material used by Willard Thorp in compiling an article for the New York Times Magazine, 1941 June 8; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 14)
        Primarily numerous responses to questionnaires sent by Thorp to 1941 college graduates, with a few notes by Thorp.
    - 3. Class Lecture Notes, 1932-1967; 1 box
      - Victorian Poets Lecture Notes (undergraduate), 1932-1952; 17 folders (Box 13, Folder 1-17)
      - American Literature Lecture Notes (undergraduate), 1936-1964; 25 folders (Box 13, Folder 18-42)
      - American Literature Lecture Notes, 1940-1966; 27 folders (Box 13, Folder 43-69)
      - Henry James Lecture Notes, 1967 (spring term), 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 70)
  - Subseries 1C: Journals and Address Book, 1923 June 29-1981; 1 box
    Willard's numerous journals reflect his personal thoughts and philosophies as well as recount travels in Europe. One contains travel expenses; another, writings in French and French vocabulary lists; a third, a selection of handwritten powms by Louis Coxe, Franklin D. Reeve, William Meredith, Bink Noll, Galway Kinnell, George Garrett, and Bruce Berlind, given to Willard on retiring from Princeton in June, 1967. There are loose journal entries (1978-1981), loose notes in French, and a journal kept by Willard and Margaret (entries by each) in England, the summer of 1930. One address book includes loose business cards and addresses.
    Not arranged according to any arrangement scheme.
    - Viaduct Exercise book, undated; 1 box (Box 14)
    - Viaduct Exercise book, undated-in French, 1 box (Box 14)
    - Cahier-100 Pages, undated; 1 box (Box 14)
    - Address Book, dates not examined; 1 box (Box 14)
    - The Spiral Notebook, undated; 1 box (Box 14)
    - Note Book, undated; 1 box (Box 14)
    - Journal undated-"No! Destroy" written on cover, 1 box (Box 14)
    - Notebook-on inside cover: "A record of the friendship and indebtedness of certain poets whose good fortune gave them access, at Princeton University, to the human and intellectual generosities...property of Willard Thorp. ", 1967 June; 1 box (Box 14)
    - Journal-first entry dated, 1923 June 29; 1 box (Box 14)
    - Journal entries, 1978-1981; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Journal kept by Willard and Margaret: England, 1930 summer; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Notes in French, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 1D: Documents (Awards, Certificates, Contracts, Genealogies, Etc.), 1972; 2 boxes
    Contains (in alphabetical order) various awards and certificates, including those from the New Jersey Civil War Centennial Commission (1965) Encyclopaedia Brittanica for being a distinguished contributor, the New Jersey Association of Teachers of English Author Award for "American Humorists" (1965), and Thorp's Doctor of Humane Letters from Kalamazoo College (June 1960). Others are oversize and located in Box 30.
    - Awards and Certificates, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Biography and Bibliography, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Contract for Redburn, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Family Genealogy, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Grades, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - J. B. Hubbell Award of the American Literature Group, Modern Language Association of America, 1972; 1 folder (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Retirement-Honorary Dinner and Article, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Vitas, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - TMs copy, 1956, General examination, Dept. of English, Princeton University, and memo regarding exam by James Thorpe, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Diplomas, 80th birthday memento, photostats of ship's records (1839) relating to Melville (?), dates not examined; 1 box (Box 30)
  - Subseries 1E: Photographs, 1940-1982 June 18; 1 box
    Consists of two bound photo albums of Willard's travels in England and France, and loose pictures of Bob and Louis Coxe, Vicki Mahaffey, Bruce Redford, Allen Tate and Caroline Gordon, family photographs, birthday parties, accepting awards at Princeton, Thorp's houses, portraits, and his summer professorship at the University of Virginia (1947).
    Photographs not in bound albums are arranged alphabetically by subject.
    - Photo Albums (2), dates not examined; 1 box (Box 16)
    - Coxe, Bob - Visit, 1982 June 18; 1 folder (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Coxe, Louis and family, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Mahaffey, Vicky and Chris Dennis with Amanda Margaret Dennis, 1982 April; 1 folder (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous photographs, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Redford, Bruce (graduate student)-family commencement party, 1981; 1 folder (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Tate, Allen and Caroline (Gordon), dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Thorp, Willard, 1940-1981; 1 box
      - birthday parties, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 16, Folder 7)
      - family photographs, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 16, Folder 8)
      - houses, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 16, Folder 9)
      - portraits, 1940-1981; 1 folder (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Princeton L.H.D., 1978; 1 folder (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - retirement party - Lowrie House, 1967 May 16; 1 folder (Box 16, Folder 12)
      - Visiting professor - Rice University, 1952-1953; 1 folder (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - University of Virginia, 1947 Summer; 1 folder (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - World War II at home, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Subseries 1F: Printed Matter, 1922-1981; 2 boxes
    Includes much of Willard's writings, including reviews, articles, as well as invitations, brochures, and catalogs.
    - "American Writing in the Twentieth Century" - reviews, 1960-1961; 1 folder (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Annuals, Journals, and Contributions to Books, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - "As the College Man Sees the War"- The New York Times Magazine, 1941 March 23; 1 folder (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Bulletins, reprints of articles, etc, 1922-1960; 1 folder (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Invitations, brochures, book catalogs, etc., dates not examined; 2 folders (Box 17, Folder 5-6)
    - Journals, newspapers, etc., dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - "The Lives of Eighteen from Princeton"-reviews, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Newspapers, 1936-1961; 1 folder (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Princeton Alumni Weekly articles, 1940-1965; 1 folder (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Reviews, 1930-1981; 1 box
      - 1930-1949, 1 folder (Box 18, Folder 4)
      - 1950-1960, 1 folder (Box 18, Folder 5)
      - 1961-1970, 1 folder (Box 18, Folder 6)
      - 1971-1981, 1 folder (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - University of Hawaii-Summer session, 1936; 1 folder (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 1G: Papers of Others, 1916-1970; 2 boxes
    Includes poems by James Beard, Louis Coxe, Robert Penn Warren, and Allen Tate, among others, as well as a collection of offprints of articles by contemporary literary scholars and critics inscribed to Thorp.
    Arranged alphabetically by author.
    - Beard, James-edition of James Fenimore Cooper letters, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Buell, Tom-"Long Distance Winter", dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Coxe, Louis O.-poems, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Rushton, J. P.-Journal in School of Military Government-Princeton, 1944; 1 folder (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Tate, Allen-inscribed copy of "The Fugitive", dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Warren, Robert Penn-poems, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous Papers of Others, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Offprints of Articles by Others, 1916-1970; 1 box (Box 32)
      Consists of approximately 110 offprints of articles by a wide range of literary critics and scholars; many of the pamphlets are inscribed by the author to Thorp. A complete list, showing author, article title, journal where published, and date (year), is kept in the box.
  - Subseries 1H: Recordings, undated; 1 box
    Consists of four reel-to-reel tapes of conversations of Thorp.
    - Conversations with Thorp, undated; 1 box (Box 31)
      Existence and Location of Copies
      32101103180145_1_a.mp3
      32101103180152_1_a.mp3
      32101103180160_1_a.mp3
      32101103180178_1_a.mp3
      32101103180178_2_a.mp3
      Consists of four reel-to-reel tapes.
- Series 2: Papers of Margaret Thorp, 1819-1962; 10 boxes
  Consists of the papers of Margaret Thorp, including writings, lectures, correspondence, journals, sketchbooks, and photographs.
  This series is arranged five subseries: Writings and Lectures, Correspondence, Journals and Notebooks, Sketchbooks, and Photographs.
  - Subseries 2A: Writings and Lectures, 1819-1951; 3 boxes
    Consists of Margaret's writings and lectures, including drafts of Charles Kingsley, 1819-1875 and Female Persuasion: Six Strong-Minded Women, notes of her subjects' lives, articles in various journals, magazines, and newspapers (1919-1924), such as The Smith Alumnae Quarterly, the Christian Science Monitor, Scribner's Magazine, and the New York Evening Post, and lectures on her writings, such as "The Lily and the Bloomer."
    Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - "American Fund for French Wounded, Weekly Bulletin"-Margaret Thorp, editor-No. 1-18, 1917 November 21-1918 March 22; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - "American Pioneers and Robert Herrick"- The Landmark, 1931 October; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Articles in various journals, magazines, and newspapers, 1919-1924; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - The Domestic Manners of the English-Willard and Margaret Thorp (drafts), dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - "Domestic Manners of the English"- Atlantic Monthly, 1934 September; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - "The Female as Artist", dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Female Persuasion: Six Strong-Minded Women, 1943-1951; 2 boxes
      - Beecher, Catherine, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 7)
      - Blackwell, Elizabeth, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 8)
      - Bloomer, Amelia, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 9)
      - Child, Lydia Maria, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 10)
      - Greenwood, Grace (Sara J. Lippincott), dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 11)
      - McCord, Louisa S., dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 20, Folder 12)
      - Stowe, Harriet Beecher, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - Swisshelm, Jane Grey, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 21, Folder 2)
      - Illustrations, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 21, Folder 3)
      - Others, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 21, Folder 4)
      - Preface, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 21, Folder 5)
      - Reviews and letters, 1949-1951; 1 folder (Box 21, Folder 6)
      - Reviews (note forms), dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 21, Folder 7)
      - Yale University Press, 1943-1949; 1 folder (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - "Hauteville House", dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - "Henry the Eighth: A Literary Sidelight"- The Landmark, 1931 December; 1 folder (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - Charles Kingsley, 1819-1875; 2 boxes
      - Dissertation-Yale University (p. 1-200), 1934; 1 folder (Box 21, Folder 11)
      - Dissertation-Yale University (p. 201-end), 1934; 1 folder (Box 22, Folder 1)
      - Drafts, dates not examined; 2 folders (Box 22, Folder 2-3)
      - Kingsley's letters (transcripts), 1852-1873; 1 folder (Box 22, Folder 4)
      - Letters, 1931-1945; 1 folder (Box 22, Folder 5)
      - Margaret Thorp's notes of Macmillan family letters as they relate to Charles Kingsley, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 22, Folder 6)
      - Notes on John Henry Newman (in relation to Charles Kingsley), dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 22, Folder 7)
      - Notes on Kingsley's articles and reviews, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 22, Folder 8)
      - Photos and illustrations, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 22, Folder 9)
      - Reviews, 1937; 1 folder (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - The Lily and the "Bloomer" lecture, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 22, Folder 11)
    - "Magistrate's Court, Bermuda", dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 22, Folder 12)
    - "The Saints' Tragedy"-notes, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 22, Folder 13)
    - "Shakespeare and the Fine Arts", dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 22, Folder 14)
    - Strong-minded Women lecture, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 22, Folder 15)
    - "Udolpho and Childe Harold"- Modern Languages Notes, 1930 April; 1 folder (Box 22, Folder 16)
  - Subseries 2B: Correspondence, 1886-1962; 1 box
    Includes family letters (1886-1957), letters from Caroline Gordon and Allen Tate (1942-1962), and Vivienne Heigh (Mrs. T. S. Eliot) (1931-1932).
    - Eliot, Vivienne Heigh (Mrs. T.S. Eliot), 1931-1932; 1 folder (Box 22, Folder 17)
    - Family Letters, 1886-1957; 1 folder (Box 22, Folder 18)
    - Tate, Allen and Caroline, 1942-1962; 1 folder (Box 22, Folder 19)
  - Subseries 2C: Journals and Notebooks, 1917-1927 August 30; 2 boxes
    Consists of journals and notebooks Margaret used to research the lives of people in her biographies. Also includes her diary kept in France during World War I (three copies, 1917-1918) and two other diaries, one kept in France in 1923 and one kept in London, July 9, 1927-August 30, 1927.
    Arranged chronologically.
    - Notebooks (2), dates not examined; 1 box (Box 23)
    - Notes of Charles Kingsley's letters (loose), dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Notebook-leather cover, dates not examined; 1 box (Box 24)
    - Notebook-paper cover, dates not examined; 1 box (Box 24)
    - Notebook-composition-labelled "Ft. Dix Library Chronicle", dates not examined; 1 box (Box 24)
    - Diary kept in France during World War I, 1917-1918; 1 box
      - (copy 1, with photographs), dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 24, Folder 1)
      - (copy 2), dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 24, Folder 2)
      - (copy 3), dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Diary kept in France: 1923 and exercises in French, 1 folder (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Diary kept in London: 1927 July 9-1927 August 30 and notes, 1 folder (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 2D: Sketchbooks, 1888-1928; 1 box
    Sketchbooks (late 1800s-early 1900s) are in various media (pencil, colored pencil, watercolor), presumably by a family member (many of them pre-date her birth) of Europe, including figures and landscapes.
    - "The Heatherley" note book- dated, 1927-1928; 1 box (Box 25)
    - "The Bainbridge" sketch book- dated, 1909; 1 box (Box 25)
    - Sketchbook-tan cloth cover-dated, 1889; 1 box (Box 25)
    - Sketchbook-tan cloth cover-dated, 1888; 1 box (Box 25)
    - Sketchbook-tan cloth cover, undated; 1 box (Box 25)
    - Sketchbook-grey cloth cover- dated, 1909-1927; 1 box (Box 25)
    - Sketchbook-green cover, dates not examined; 1 box (Box 25)
    - Sketchbook-burgundy cover, dates not examined; 1 box (Box 25)
    - Sketchbook-green and yellow cover- dated, 1923-1925; 1 box (Box 25)
    - "Newark Academy" sketch books (3), dates not examined; 1 box (Box 25)
    - Loose-leaf sketches (2)-on House of Commons stationery, dates not examined; 1 box (Box 25)
  - Subseries 2E: Photographs, 1899; 4 boxes
    Consists of (family) photographs. One album (dated) contains photographs of Margaret and her family when she was a child, and numerous bound, undated albums of unidentified persons.
    - Photograph album-black cover-dated, 1899; 1 box (Box 26)
    - Photograph album-tan cover, dates not examined; 1 box (Box 26)
    - Photo-in blue velvet frame, dates not examined; 1 box (Box 27)
    - Photo-in black wood frame, dates not examined; 1 box (Box 27)
    - Photo album-brown leather cover, dates not examined; 1 box (Box 27)
    - Photo-in large purple velvet frame, dates not examined; 1 box (Box 28)
    - Photo-in small purple velvet frame, dates not examined; 1 box (Box 28)
    - Photo-in small brown wood frame, dates not examined; 1 box (Box 28)
    - Portrait photo-Sarony, dates not examined; 1 box (Box 28)
    - Photo album-brown leather cover, dates not examined; 1 box (Box 28)
    - Photo album-brown leather cover, dates not examined; 1 box (Box 29)
    - Family photographs, dates not examined; 1 folder (Box 29, Folder 1)